<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="howto.remote" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>HowTo - Interact with the OPENENGSB Remotely</title>

  <section xml:id="howto.remote.jms">
    <title>Using JMS proxying</title>
    <para>The current JMS Connector allows for internal method calls being redirected via JMS as well as internal
      services being called.</para>
    <para>For resources regarding JMS please take a look at the according <link
        xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_Message_Service">Wikipedia Page</link> and for specific language
      bindings take a look at <link xlink:href="http://activemq.apache.org/connectivity.html">ActiveMQ</link></para>
    <section>
      <title>Proxying internal Connector calls</title>
      <para>Whenever now a method is sent through the JMS Port the call is marshalled and sent via JMS to a queue named
        "receive"". The marshalling is done via JSON. The mapping has the parameters methodName, args, classes, metadata
        and potentially answer and callId. methodName gives the name of the method to call. Args are the serialised
        parameters of the method. classes are the types of the arguments. This way it is easy to unmarshall the args
        into the appropriate classes. metadata is a simple Map which stores key value pairs. answer can simply be yes or
        no and denotes if the methodcall wants an answer to the call. callId gives the return queue the caller will
        listen to for an answer. </para>
      <para>An answer can have the type, arg, className and metaData properties. type can be Object, Exception or Void.
        arg is the serialised form of the return argument. className is the runtime class of the arg for
        deserialisation. metadata is a simple key value store. </para>
      <section>
        <title>HowTo call an external service via proxies</title>
        <para>This section will give a short introduction how to instantiate a proxy and call an external
          connector</para>
        <para>First you have to go to the TestClient to instantiate a new Proxy. Select the Domain you want to have
          proxied and click New Proxy for that Domain.</para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata id="testclient" fileref="graphics/testclient.png" format="png" width="300" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>Testclient new proxy link</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>Then you have to set the correct values for the proxy properties. The Service Id is a unique value that
          identifies the proxy in the OPENENGSB system. The Port Id defines to Port to be used for sending the request.
          "jms-json" is a currently supported Port that sends the request via a json encoded JMS message. The
          destination describes the endpoint the message should be sent to. When using jms-json the domain and port of
          the JMS provider have to be set. When calling a remote connector the unique id of the remote service or
          connector has to be provided. This way the remote service can identify, load and call a certain service. If
          the call is not intended to go to another OPENENGSB, or the external service needs no identification of the
          service to call the remote service id can be omitted.</para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata id="create-proxy" fileref="graphics/create-proxy.png" format="png" width="400" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>Create Proxy</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>After saving the proxy you should be able to test it via the TestClient page. Following is an example of
          an unsecured call:</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[{
  "authenticationData": {
    "className":"org.openengsb.core.api.security.model.UsernamePasswordAuthenticationInfo",
    "data": {
      "username":"admin",
      "password":"password"
    }
  },
  "timestamp":42,
  "message": {
    "callId":"xyz",
    "answer":true,
    "methodCall": {
      "classes": [
        "java.lang.String",
        "org.openengsb.core.api.workflow.model.ProcessBag"
      ],
      "methodName": "executeWorkflow",
      "metaData": {
        "serviceFilter": "(objectClass=org.openengsb.core.api.workflow.WorkflowService)",
        "contextId": "foo"
      },
      "args": [
        "simpleFlow",
        {
        }
      ]
    }
  }
}]]></programlisting>
        <para> IF you would like to use security instead you should prefer the following call: <programlisting><![CDATA[{
{
  "encryptedContent":"encodedMessage", // Base 64 and encryped string of the message above
  "encryptedKey":"encodedKey" // The encoded key
}]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata id="call-proxy" fileref="graphics/call-proxy.png" format="png" width="400" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>Test a proxy</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>When proxying connector calls you have to provide an answer to every call, as the system blocks until it
          gets an answer. You have to send a JSON message containing a type string parameter, which can be Object,
          Exception or Void depending on the return argument of the method, arg where you simply serialise the Return
          Object, so it can be deserialised into the correct object later and className which gives the exact class that
          has to be used for deserialisation. The request contains a parameter callId which is the name of the queue the
          answer has to be sent to.</para>
        <programlisting>{"type":"Object","className":"org.openengsb.core.ports.jms.JMSPortTest$TestClass",
          "metaData":{"test":"test"},"arg":{"test":"test"}}</programlisting>
        <para>Whenever a call to this proxy is then made a new JMS message will be sent to the "receive" queue on the
          destination you entered. The exact make up of the message was already described. When implementing an external
          connector it is best to test the call you want to receive first via the TestClient, so you get the exact
          message that you will have to work with.</para>
        <para>Please always keep in mind security. By default security is turned on. If you want to turn it off please
          take a look into the <code>etc/system.properties</code> file. While using no security for testing is very
          interesting we would not advise you to send unencrypted messages in a production environment.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Calling internal Services</title>
      <para>To call an internal Service send a methodcall as described before to the "receive" queue on the server you
        want to call. The service works exactly as defined before. There currently are two ways of specifying which
        service to address. <itemizedlist>
          <listitem> serviceId: This will call the service that was exported with the specified "id"-property. It
            behaves like the following Filter in OSGi-syntax: <code>(id=&lt;serviceId&gt;)</code>
          </listitem>
          <listitem> serviceFilter: This way you can specify any filter in OSGi-syntax to adress the service, so it is
            not necessary to bind the client to a specific id, but to other properties as well (e.g.
              <code>location.root</code>, <code>location.&lt;context&gt;</code>, <code>objectClass</code>, ...)
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> You can also use both attributes (serviceId and serviceFilter). It will create a filter matching
        both constraints. </para>

      <para>Example: if you want to execute a workflow via the WorkflowService send</para>
      <code>{"callId":"12345","answer":true,"classes":["java.lang.String",
        "org.openengsb.core.api.workflow.model.ProcessBag"],
        "methodName":"executeWorkflow","metaData":{"serviceId":"workflowService",
        "contextId":"foo"},"args":["simpleFlow", {}]}</code>
      <para>Please be aware that the flow the above method tries to call (simpleFlow) is not available by default on the
        OpenEngSB. To make sure that there's a flow you can call install the flow in the OpenEngSB. Therefore start the
        OpenEngSB and go to the <link xlink:href="http://localhost:8090/openengsb/SendEventPage/">SendEventPage</link>.
        There choose to create a new process and press new. Now enter simpleFlow as processname and past the following
        process: <programlisting><![CDATA[<process xs:schemaLocation="http://drools.org/drools-5.0/process 
  drools-processes-5.0.xsd" type="RuleFlow" name="simpleFlow" id="simpleFlow" 
  package-name="org.openengsb" xmlns="http://drools.org/drools-5.0/process" 
  xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
 <header>
  <variables>
   <variable name="processBag">
    <type name="org.drools.process.core.datatype.impl.type.ObjectDataType" 
     className="org.openengsb.core.api.workflow.model.ProcessBag"/>
   </variable>
  </variables>
 </header>
 <nodes>
  <start id="1" name="Start" x="16" y="16" width="91" height="48"/>
  <end id="2" name="End" x="21" y="168" width="80" height="40"/>
  <actionNode id="3" name="Action" x="21" y="96" width="80" height="40">
   <action type="expression" dialect="mvel">
    processBag.addProperty("test", 42);
    processBag.addProperty("alternativeName", "The answer to life the universe and everything");
   </action>
  </actionNode>
 </nodes>
 <connections>
  <connection from="3" to="2"/>
  <connection from="1" to="3"/>
 </connections>
</process>]]></programlisting> After pressing save you can access the process via the message shown above. </para>
      <para>to the receive queue on the OPENENGSB JMS Port which is started by default on Port 6549. Make sure that
        classes and args has the same number of arguments. If you just want an object to be instantiated, but have no
        corresponding values that should be set for the object simply add {} (as in the example above) which will
        instantiate the object but recognize, that no values have to be set on the object. {"name" : "SomeName"} would
        on the other hand call the setName method with SomeName.</para>
      <para>The response to the above message will be returned on a queue you've pasted via the callId field.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <para> We provide examples in different languages how to connect to the OpenEngSB. The examples are grouped
        according to language and the documentation to the different examples are directly done in the code of the
        examples. We try to keep those examples as good as possible up-to-date, but do not gurantee that they all work
        as expected since we can't add them to our integration tests. If you want to provide examples in different
        languages you're always welcomed to provide them. </para>
      <section>
        <title>Connect With Python</title>
        <para>To test the OPENENGSB JMS implementation with Python please follow the <link
            xlink:href="${github}/docs/examples/src/main/python/PythonClient.txt">instructions</link>
        </para>
        <para>The example can be downloaded <link xlink:href="${repos.example}-python.zip">here</link></para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="developer.plugins.csharp">
        <title>Connect With CSharp</title>
        <para>The CSharp connector is written on basis of the Apache ActiveMQ JMS connector. There an EngSB.sln file.
          This project file has been developed with SharpDevelop 4, but is also tested with VisualStudio 2008 CSharp
          Express Edition with the .Net Framework 4.</para>
        <para>The example can be downloaded <link xlink:href="${repos.example}-csharp.zip">here</link></para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="developer.plugins.perl">
        <title>Connect With Perl</title>
        <para>As shown in this example you can connect to the OpenEngSB in a similar way as with Python or
          CSharp.</para>
        <para>The example can be downloaded <link xlink:href="${repos.example}-perl.zip">here</link></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using WS Proxing</title>
    <para>TBW(<link xlink:href="http://issues.openengsb.org/jira/browse/OPENENGSB-2507">Jira-ISSUE</link>)</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Internal Specialities</title>
    <para>Basically there is nothing special to do to get up a service. Still, since java has no static type information
      there is no possibility to marshal things like a <code>java.util.List</code> of options. The fix we've introduced
      for this problem is to annotate parameters and define a custom marshaller. Therefore create a class with a default
      constructor extending CustomJsonMarshaller. Then annotate the parameter of the implementations you're using with
      the UseCustomJasonMarshaller annotation adding the Marshaller class. That's it. The framework will automatically
      create the mapper and call the transform method for you. </para>
    <para> Since there is an issue right now with Aries Proxies hiding parameter annotations the
      CustomMarshallerRealTypeAccess interface provides a workaround for the problem. In case this interface is found
      the class provided by it is used for searching. Otherwise the class directly is scanned.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
