<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="contributor.ekb" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">
    
    <title>Engineering Knowledge Base - EKB</title>
    <para>
        The EKB, as it is now, is at the very beginning of its development, so there is not much to write here for now.
        The most important thing which is provided by the EKB at the moment is the <link linkend="developer.ekb.queryservice">QueryService</link>.
    </para>
    
    <section>
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <para>
            The main idea for the introduction of the EKB is the idea to provide automatic transformations of domain models
            between tools and the OpenEngSB. But soon it was clear that this will not the only task the EKB should provide.
        </para>
        <para>
            Some other things the EKB shall provide when it is finished will be the QueryInterface service which represents
            the loading force of models from the EDB (this is already implemented), the possibility to provide better conflict
            checkers for the EDB and if possible automatic conflict solving.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section  xml:id='contributor.ekb.queryservice'>
        <title>Query Service</title>
        <para>
            This service has the task to load models from the EDB. Since models are no real objects but
            proxied interfaces, this service has to create a new model instance. This new model instance
            is initialised with the data which is loaded from the EDB. After all loaded data is inserted,
            the user can start work with this model. All transformations are done in this service. The user
            doesn't have to worry about that. In fact, he won't even notice that all this steps were 
            necessary.
        </para>
        <para>
            The query service provide a list of possibilities how to load models from the EDB (e.g. based on the model id or
            based on the key value pairs of the model).
        </para>            
    </section>
    
</chapter>
