<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="contributor.models" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">
    
    <title>OpenEngSBModels</title>
    <para>
        The OpenEngSBModels are the base concept for the whole semantic part of the OpenEngSB. They are needed to enable the 
        persisting of domain models into the EDB. Also they give the OpenEngSB the possibility to send models via remote and 
        to hide complexity from the user.
    </para>
    
    <section>
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <para>
            The idea behind the concept of the OpenEngSBModels or domain models is corelated to the domain/connector structure
            of the OpenEngSB. Models should represent the objects used by a domain in an abstract manner (e.g. the model "Issue"
            in the issue domain). Since such models are defined on the domain level. All connectors, which belong to a specific
            domain, use the models defined by this domain. In that way every connector of a specific domain "speaks the same
            language".
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Structure of a model</title>
        <para>
            A model is a Java bean object. This object need to be annotated with the @Model annotation of the core api bundle.
            An object that is marked that way will be enhanced by a weaving hook in the OpenEngSB environment to fulfill
            all needed functionality of a model. During this enhancement the OpenEngSBModel interface is added to the object 
            and the interface methods get generated and injected.
        </para>
        <para>
            Every OpenEngSBModel object has four defined functions: getOpenEngSBModelEntries, addOpenEngSBModelEntry,
            deletOpenEngSBModelEntry and retrieveInternalModelId.
            Whenever getOpenEngSBModelEntries is called, the model transform itself into a list of key/value pairs, where every entry have 
            in addition the type of the value saved. This mechanism is used for easier saving of models to the EDB and also to transfer
            a model to a different machine. With the addOpenEngSBModelEntry you can add additional entries which are not part of the model
            definition itself to the model. With the removeOpenEngSBModelEntry you can manually remove an entry which has been inserted 
            manually through addOpenEngSBModelEntry. Finally the retrieveInternamModelId method returns the internal id of the model. How
            such an id is set, will be explained later.
        </para>
        <para>
            To enable all funcationality of a model (inlcuding transformations) this model need to be provided through the labs delegation
            project. To do so, add the labs delegation project to your models bundle and annotate the model class with the annotation
            @Provide. For this annotation you have to set the context for the model providing to the constant DELEGATION_CONTEXT_MODELS 
            of the core api constants.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Supported field types</title>
        <para>
            Currently the models are able to work with the wrappers of primitive types(Integer, Boolean, ...), strings, dates, lists, 
            maps, models and files. All those objects can be used in the models and they get in the generated list of OpenEngSBModelEntries
            created by the getOpenEngSBModelEntries method. These entries will be persisted in the EDB (see the chapter about the EDB for
            more details).
        </para>
        <para>
            If you have fields which are needed by your model, but you do not want that this fields get persisted, you can annotate this
            fields with the annotation @IgnoredModelField. The so marked fields are ignored during the model entries generation.
        </para>
        <para>
            Special case in the supported field types are File objects. They are quite tricky, especially if the models shall be
            transfered to another machine. The behaviour of the models are: Whenever a model have to transform itself
            to a list of OpenEngSBModelEntry, the model is aware of file objects. If it finds a file object, it creates a 
            FileWrapper object out of it. A FileWrapper object contains the name of the file and a byte array which holds the 
            zip compressed content of the file object.
        </para>
        <para>
            If such a FileWrapper would be accessed by a getter of a File object, the ModelUtils does the conversion work of the
            FileWrapper to the file object for you. So this feature is completely transparent to the normal user. 
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Model Ids</title>
        <para>
            For easier maintaining and faster finding of models (and also to enable the versioning possibility), the user is able 
            to define a field to be the id of a model. An important point to consider here is that this id has to be unique for a 
            connector of a domain (this is because the id will be enlarged with the domain id and the connector id). Also this id
            needs to implement the toString() method accordingly. The easiest way is to use a String as identifier.
        </para>
        <para>
            To define a field to be the id of the model you simply have to add an annotation to the corresponding field. The 
            annotation is called OpenEngSBModelId. If no id is defined for a model and this model has to be inserted into the
            EDB, the EDB just take an arbitrary id to save the model.
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
