<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2010 OpenEngSB Division, Vienna University of Technology

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="what.is.openengsb" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>What is the Open Engineering Service Bus</title>

  <para> In engineering environments a lot of different tools are used. Most of these operate on the same domain, but
    often interoperability is the limiting factor. For each new project and team member tool integration has to be
    repeated again. In general, this ends up with numerous point-to-point connectors between tools which are neither
    stable solutions nor flexible ones. </para>

  <para> This is the point where the Open (Software) Engineering Service Bus (OpenEngSB) comes into play. It simplifies
    design and implementation of workflows in an engineering team. The engineering team itself (or a process
    administrator) is able to design workflows between different tools. The entire description process happens on the
    layer of generic domains instead of specific tool properties. This provides an out of the box solution which allows
    typical engineering teams to optimize their processes and make their workflows very flexible and easy to change.
    Also, OpenEngSB simplifies the replacement of individual tools and allows interdepartmental tool integration. </para>

  <para> Project management is set to a new level since its possible to clearly guard all integrated tools and
    workflows. This offers new ways in notifying managers at the right moment and furthermore allows a very general,
    distanced and objective view on a project. </para>

  <para> Although this concept is very powerful it cannot solve every problem. The OpenEngSB is not designed as a
    general graphical layer over an Enterprise Service Bus (ESB) which allows you to design ALL of your processes out of
    the box. As long as you work in the designed domains of the OpenEngSB you have a lot of graphical support and other
    tools available making your work extremely easy. But when leaving the common engineering domains you also leave the
    core scope of the service bus. OpenEngSB still allows you to connect your own integration projects, use services and
    react on events, but you have to keep in mind that you're working outside the OpenEngSB and "falling back" to
    classical Enterprise Application Integration (EAI) patterns and tools. </para>

  <para> However, this project does not try to reinvent the wheel. OpenEngSB will not replace the tools already used for
    your development process, it will integrate them. Our service bus is used to connect the different tools and design
    a workflow between them, but not to replace them with yet another application. For example, software engineers like
    us love their tools and will fight desperately if you try to take them away. We like the wheels as they are, but we
    do not like the way they are put together at the moment. </para>

</chapter>