<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2010 OpenEngSB Division, Vienna University of Technology

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="developer.release" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>Release and Release Process</title>

  <para>This section provides a step by step description to execute a release of the OpenEngSB. It is relevant for 
  everyone marked in the <ulink url="http://openengsb.org/team-list.html">OpenEngSB Team List</ulink> as release
  manager because only they have the required rights to execute the following steps.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Releases and the OpenEngSB</title>
    <para>Every release of the OpenEngSB consists of the following parts: RELEASE.MAYOR.MINOR.TYPE. Every release
    of this type is available at <ulink url="http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/">Maven Central</ulink>. Optinally 
    SNAPSHOT is appended. Snapshot releases are available from the
    <ulink url="https://oss.sonatype.org/content/groups/public/">Sonatype Snapshot repository</ulink>. This section
    explains what each modifier means and how it is used within the OpenEngSB.</para>

    <para>SNAPSHOTS: Snapshots are always available from the latest build of the OpenEngSB. They are taken from the
    master branch automatically at each commit.</para>
  
    <para>TYPE: Type could be MX, RCX or RELEASE, where X is a number. While RELEASE marks a final release, ready for
    use in your production environment, M and RC are typically not ready for production. M stands for Milestone
    release and is cut every two weeks to present the current state of the OpenEngSB and allow a coarse grained 
    planning and roadmap for the OpenEngSB team. RC, release candidates, are handled differently. After everything is
    finished and the OpenEngSB teams think that the current work is ready for a release, we provide a release candidate
    and invite everyone to test the release. If there are any issues with the release we fix them and provide another 
    release candidate. During this process no new features, but only bug fixes are handled. We continue this process as
    long as there are no new bug reports for a RC for two weeks. Then we re-release the latest release candidate as
    final release. This process only applies for RELEASE and MAYOR. MINOR is handled differently, as explained later
    on.</para>

    <para>RELEASE is a increasing number used for mayor changes within the OpenEngSB architecture. In addition all
    methods and interfaces marked as deprecated are removed during such a release. It is also possible that a
    RELEASE does not enhance any mayor architectural concept but is only used to get rid of all the deprecated
    methods, generated during MAYOR releases.</para>

    <para>MAYOR is the main feature development number of the OpenEngSB. Each release containing new features will be
    a MAYOR release. Nevertheless, between MAYOR releases architectural concepts are not removed but only set to
    deprecated. This means they only enhance functionality but try to not break with former releases.</para>

    <para>MINOR releases are bug-fix releases. They do not include any new features but only fix bugs within the
    OpenEngSB. They have no release plan, but are simply cut after each bug-fix.</para>

    <para>To visualize the explained process the following example. Assume we have released openengsb-1.0.0.RELEASE.
    Now we're working on openengsb-1.1.0.RELEASE. Therefore we start developing openengsb-1.1.0.M1 which will be
    released in two weeks. During the development of 1.1.0.M1 a bug occurs at openengsb-1.0.0.RELEASE. During the
    development the bug is fixed and openengsb-1.0.1.RELEASE is released. After 1.1.0.M1 we require three additional
    milestone releases to get feature releases. Six weeks after 1.1.0.M1 we'll release 1.1.0.RC1. From now on we 
    continue to develop 1.2.0.M1 (or 2.0.0.M1, depending on the gravity of the changes) and wait for feedback on 
    1.1.0.RC1. Now a bug-report occurs for 1.0.1.RELEASE. We fix the bug, release 1.0.2.RELEASE with the fix. If
    it also affects 1.1.0.RC1, we fix the bug there too and release 1.1.0.RC2 (still working on 1.2.0.M1(!)). Now 
    assume that some other bug reports are received for 1.0.0.RC2. We fix them and release 1.1.0.RC3. In the meantime 
    we finished 1.2.0.M1 and start work on 1.2.0.M2. Now two weeks after the release of 1.1.0.RC3 without any new 
    bug-reports we re-release 1.1.0.RC3 to 1.1.0.RELEASE (starting the game again from the beginning).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configure Maven</title>
    <para>For the right rights to deploy to maven central and upload maven site to openengsb.org the following
    entries are required in your ~/.m2/settings.xml file:
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<settings>
  <server>
    <id>sonatype-nexus-snapshots</id>
    <username>SONATYPE_USERNAME</username>
    <password>SONATYPE_PASSWORD</password>
  </server>
  <server>
    <id>sonatype-nexus-staging</id>
    <username>SONATYPE_USERNAME</username>
    <password>SONATYPE_PASSWORD</password>
  </server>
  <server>
    <id>OpenengsbWebServer</id>
    <username>OPENENGSB_SERVER_USERNAME</username>
    <password>OPENEGNSB_SERVER_PASSWORD</password>
  </server>
  <profiles>
    <profile>
      <id>milestone</id>
      <properties>
        <gpg.passphrase>GPG_PASSPHRASE</gpg.passphrase>
      </properties>
    </profile>
    <profile>
      <id>release</id>
      <properties>
        <gpg.passphrase>GPG_PASSPHRASE</gpg.passphrase>
      </properties>
    </profile>
    <profile>
      <id>final</id>
      <properties>
        <gpg.passphrase>GPG_PASSPHRASE</gpg.passphrase>
      </properties>
    </profile>
  </profiles>
<settings>]]></programlisting></para>

    <para>All the usernames and passwords can be retrieved from someone marked as administrator in the
    <ulink url="http://openengsb.org/team-list.html">OpenEngSB Team List</ulink>.</para>

    <para>In addition you have to have a GPG key for your mail address (the same you're using to commit to the 
    OpenEngSB source repository which is uploaded to the <ulink url="hkp://pgp.mit.edu/">MIT Key Server</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Adapt JIRA</title>
    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Perform the release</title>
    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Spread the News</title>
    <para></para>
  </section>

</chapter>

