<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="developer.projectroles" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>Project Roles</title>

  <para>This section describes the how the roles in the OpenEngSB Project are defined.</para>

  <para>Basically the OpenEngSB is, from it's structure exactly as any Apache Software Foundation 
    (ASF) project.  We split the different roles in User, Contributor, Commiters and Project Comitee 
    Members. In addition the OpenEngSB is developed in a metocracy, similar to ASF the persons
    doing the most affect the project most. Basically the only reason we're not an ASF project
    is that we prefer using GIT :)
  </para>

  <section xml:id="developer.projectroles.user">
    <title>Users</title>
    <para>Users are persons using the OpenEngSB.</para>
    <para>
      This group does not contribute in the OpenEngSB project in any way. They download the
      OpenEngSB, use it and may ask questions in the IRC channel or on the mailing lists.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="developer.projectroles.contributor">
    <title>Contributors</title>
    <para>Contributors are users who contribute ideas, issues or pull requests.</para>
    <para>
      Basically the only difference between users and contributors are that they actively
      contribute to the OpenEngSB in one or another way. Those users have full rights on
      the issue tracker after they've created an account but are not allowed to access the
      OpenEngSB core repos with write karma.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="developer.projectroles.commiter">
    <title>Commiters</title>
    <para>
      Commiters have the same rights as contributors with the difference that they have
      wirte access to the OpenEngSB Github repositories. They are allowed to directly push
      changes, but also should review pull-requests.
    </para>
    <para>
      To become a commiter a person have to be active on different parts of the OpenEngSB.
      Provide patches, write documentation, answer on the user mailing list and the IRC
      channel. If a contributor is active for an undefined time the project comitee members may 
      vote to add a contributor to a commiter.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="developer.projectroles.pmc">
    <title>Project Comitee Members</title>
    <para>
      Project comitee members have the same rights as commiters, with the difference that they
      are responsible for the project. PMCs relese the OpenEngSB, vote contributors to commiters
      and commiters to PMCs.
    </para>
    <para>Every commiter can become a PMC through active contribution to the OpenEngSB.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>

