<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="howto.supportedfield" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

    <title>How to add new field support for domain models</title>

    <section>
        <title>Goal</title>
        <para>
            This tutorial explains how to create new supported field types for domain models. What a domain model is, can be
            read in the user manual in the semantics section(<xref linkend="user.semantics" />). In this section is also explained
            which fields are supported until now. This task is divided in two subtasks, where the second one is optional. The first
            subtask provides the functionality that the model is working correctly with the new field type. The second subtask is
            the possibility that this fields are also saved in the EDB and can be loaded from the EDB.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Time to complete</title>
        <para>
            If you are already familiar with the OpenEngSB the first subtask will take about 45 minutes. The second subtask 
            will take about another 45 minutes. If you are not familiar with the OpenEngSB please read this manual from the 
            start or check the <link xlink:href="http://www.openengsb.org">homepage</link> for further information.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Prerequisites</title>
        <para>
            For information about how to get started as contributor to the OpenEngSB project and how to
            get the current OpenEngSB source please read the contributor section of the manual: 
            <xref linkend="contributor.manual" />.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Subtask 1 - Add model support</title>
        <para>
            All that have to be done is to add a new converter step to the ModelProxy class in the core common bundle. Step by
            step:
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Create new converter step</title>
            <para>
                A converter step is a class which extends the interface ModelEntryConverterStep. A ModelEntryConverterStep 
                interface consists of 4 methods. This methods are 2 match functions, which define if the given object can
                be converted by one of the converter methods, which are the other 2 functions. The interface looks like this:
            </para>
            <programlisting>
                public interface ModelEntryConverterStep {
                   /**
                    * Checks if the given object is suitable for converting work when "getOpenEngSBModelObjects" of the proxy is
                    * called. (e.g. an OpenEngSBModel)
                   */
                   boolean matchForGetModelEntries(Object object);
                   /**
                    * Does the converting work for the proxy when "getOpenEngSBModelObjects" is called. (e.g. OpenEngSBModel ->
                    * OpenEngSBModelWrapper)
                   */
                   Object convertForGetModelEntries(Object object);
                   /**
                    * Checks if the given object is suitable for converting work when a getter of the proxy is called. (e.g. an
                    * OpenEngSBModelWrapper)
                   */
                   boolean matchForGetter(Object object);
                   /**
                    * Does the converting work for the proxy when a getter is called. (e.g. OpenEngSBModelWrapper ->
                    * OpenEngSBModel)
                   */
                   Object convertForGetter(Object object);
                }
            </programlisting>
            <para>
                The first two functions define the converting functionality if getOpenEngSBModelObjects is called. (e.g. we used
                this to convert a File object to a FileWrapper object).
                The other two functions define the converting functionality if a corresponding getter method is called. (e.g. convert
                FileWrapper object to File object.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Add converter step</title>
            <para>
                To add the new converter step, you have to add the converter step to the list of converter steps in the method
                "initializeModelConverterSteps" in the ModelProxyHandler class. Important: The DefaultConverterStep have to be
                the last step in the converter step list.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Subtask 2 - Add EDB support</title>
        <para>
            To accomplish this task, the EDB and the EKB has to be extended. WARNING: This step is currently under construction
            and very likely to be changed soon. As example for this subtask, you can check how it was done with the File object.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Extend EDB</title>
            <para>
                To extend the EDB, the method "convertSubModel" in the class JPADatabase of the EDB bundle has to be extended. In the 
                part where every OpenEngSBModelEntry get analyzed, a new if statement has to be added, which does a special handling
                if the new introduced wrapper class is the parameter. How this wrapper class is saved, is up to you. 
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Extend EKB</title>
            <para>
                To extend the EKB, you have to extend the method "getValueForProperty" of the QueryInterfaceService in the EKB bundle.
                Again, here must also a new if statement been added, where the parameter type is checked for the new field object which
                should be supported. If this statement fits, you have to undo the conversion which have you done in the "Extend EDB" part.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
