<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="architecture" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>Architecture of the OpenEngSB</title>

  <para>This chapter tries to give a short summary of the most important concepts in the OpenEngSB architecture.</para>

  <para>The following graphic shows the architecture of the OpenEngSB. In the center we use a bus system
  to integrate different modules. In this case we do not use a classical Enterprise Service Bus (ESB), but rather the
  OSGi service infrastructure via Spring-DM (<xref linkend="architecture.concept.esb" />). We are using <link xlink:href="http://karaf.apache.org">Apache Karaf</link> as the OSGi
  environment. Karaf is used in this case, instead of a most basic OSGi environment, such as 
  <link xlink:href="http://felix.apache.org">Apache Felix</link> or 
  <link xlink:href="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse Equinox</link> , because it supports us with additional features as 
  extended console support and the feature definitions.
  This base infrastructure, including all modifications required for the OpenEngSB is called the 
  <xref linkend="architecture.concept.infrastructure" />. Within the OpenEngSB 
  Infrastructure so called <xref linkend="architecture.concept.components" /> and 
  <xref linkend="architecture.concept.tooldomains" /> are installed. Both
  types are written in a JVM compatible language, including OSGi configuration files to run in the OpenEngSB 
  Infrastructure. They are explained later within this chapter. Different tools running outside the OpenEngSB 
  Infrastructure are called <xref linkend="architecture.concept.clienttools" /> or 
  <xref linkend="architecture.concept.domaintools" />, depending on their usage scenario. 
  To integrate and use them within the OpenEngSB so called 
  <xref linkend="architecture.concept.connectors" /> are used. All of these concepts are explained 
  within the next sections.</para>

  <para>
    <mediaobject>
      <alt>Technical view of the OpenEngSB highlighting the most important concepts of the integration system.</alt>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="graphics/extendedEngSB.png" format="png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption><para>Technical view of the OpenEngSB highlighting the most important concepts of the integration system</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </para>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.esb">
    <title>OpenEngSB Enterprise Service Bus (ESB)</title>
    <para>One of the principal concepts for the OpenEngSB development is (if possible) 
    to use already existing and proven solutions rather than inventing new ones. In this manner the OpenEngSB is an 
    extension to the ESB concept. Typical ESBs such as 
    <link xlink:href="http://servicemix.apache.org">Apache Servicemix</link> or other JBI or ESB implementations 
    always have the feeling to be huge and bloated. Complex integration patterns, messaging, huge configuration files
    and similar concepts/problems lead to this feeling. And those feelings are right. They are bloated. The OpenEngsB
    tries a different approach. Using Karaf as its base framework the environment is VERY lightweight. Depending on 
    your use case you can use different configurations and packages out of the box.</para>
  </section>
 
  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.infrastructure">
    <title>OpenEngSB Infrastructure</title>
    <para>While Apache Karaf provides a rich environment and functionality we're not done with it. Via the Spring-DM
    extension mechanism, AOP and the OSGi listener model the OpenEngSB directly extends the environment to provide
    own commands for the console, fine grained security and a full grown workflow model. These extensions are optional
    and not required if you want to use the platform alone. Add or remove them as required for your use case.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.components">
    <title>OpenEngSB Components</title>
    <para>These libraries are the OpenEngSB core. The core is responsible to provide the OpenEngSB infrastructure
    as well as general services such as persistence, security and workflows. To provide best integration most of
    these components are tied to the OpenEngSB ESB environment. Nevertheless, feel free to add or remove them
    as required for your use case.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.tooldomains">
    <title>OpenEngSB Tool Domains</title>
    <para>Although each tool provider gives a personal touch to its product their design is driven by a specific 
    purpose. For example, there are many different issue trackers available, each having its own advantages and 
    disadvantages, but all of them can create issues, assign and delete them. Tool Domains are based on this idea 
    and distill the common functionality for such a group of tools into one Tool Domain interface (and component).
    Tool domains could be compared best to the concept of abstract classes in in object orientated programming 
    languages. Similar to these, they can contain code, workflows, additional logic and data, but they are useless 
    without a concrete implementation. Together with the ESB, the OpenEngSB infrastructure and the core components 
    the tool domains finally result in the OpenEngSB.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.clienttools">
    <title>Client Tools (Service Consumer)</title>
    <para>Client Tools in the OpenEngSB concept are tools which do not provide any 
    services, but consume services provided by Tool Domains and Core Components instead. A classical example from 
    software engineering for a client tool is the Integrated Development Environment (IDE). Developer prefer to 
    have the entire development environment, reaching from the tickets for a project to its build results, at
    hand. On the other hand they do not need to provide any services.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.domaintools">
    <title>Domain Tools (Service Provider)</title>
    <para>Domain Tools (Service Provider) Domain Tools, compared to Client Tools, denote the other extreme of only 
    providing services. Classically, single purpose server tools, like issue tracker or chat server, match the 
    category of Domain Tools best. Most tools in (software+) engineering environments fit of course in both 
    categories, but since there are significant technically differences between them they are 
    described as two different component types.
</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.connectors">
    <title>Domain- and Client Tool Connectors</title>
    <para>Tool Connectors connect tools to the OpenEngSB environment. They implement the respective
    Tool Domain interface. As Client Tool Connectors they provide a Client Tool with 
    an access to the OpenEngSB services. Again, Domain- and Client Tool Connectors are mostly mixed up but 
    separated because of their technical differences. Additionally it is worth mentioning that 
    tools can be integrated with more than one connector. This allows one tool to act in many different domains. 
    Apache Maven is an example for such multi-purpose tools, relevant for build, as well as test and deploy of Java 
    projects.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="architecture.concept.edb">
    <title>EDB (Engineering Data Base)</title>
    <para>The EDB is a database with additional versioning feature. Its main job is to save and version 
    so called tool data. Tool data are information units which are used by tools which are connect to
    the edb.
    The connection between the tools and the EDB is done through the EngineeringDatabaseService provided
    by the core/edb bundle. This service gets a datasource (database) from the infrastructure/jpa bundle.
    The EngineeringDatabaseService is implemented with JPA, that means that every database which support
    JPA can be used as database backend for the EDB.
    As standard database backend was the H2 database chosen. But with the open concept of jpa this can be
    replaced with a more performant one.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>

