<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2010 OpenEngSB Division, Vienna University of Technology

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="when.to.use" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

    <title>When to use the OpenEngSB</title>

    <para>The OpenEngSB project has several direct purposes which should be explained within this chapter to make clear in which
    situations the OpenEngSB can be useful for you.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>The OpenEngSB as Base Environment</title>
        <para>OSGi is a very popular integration environment. Instead of delivering one big product the products get separated into
        minor parts and deployed within a general envioronment. The problem with this concept is to get old, well known concepts
        up and running in the new environment. In addition tools such as PAX construct allow a better integration into Apache Maven, 
        and extended OSGi runtimes, such as Karaf allow a richer and easier development. Neverthless, settting up such a system for 
        development means a lot of hard manual work. Using the OpenEngSB such systems can be setup within minutes.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Reusing integration Components and Workflows</title>
        <para>The OpenEngSB introduces a new level of ESB. Development with all typical ESBs mean to start from the ground and
        develop a complete, own environment, only using existing connectors. Using the OpenEngSB not only connectors but
        an entire integrated process, workflow and event environment waits for you. In addition connectors to different tools can
        not only be adapted to the specific needs, but also simply replaced by other connectors, using the Domain concept.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Management Environment</title>
        <para>The OpenEngSB delivers a complete management and monitoring environment. While this environment can
        be added to your project standalone (similar to e.g. Tomcat management console) you also have the possibility to
        completely integrate the OpenEngSB management enviornment into your Apache Wicket application.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Simple Development and Distribution Management</title>
        <para> While typical ESB have to be installed seperately from your application the OpenEngSB is delivered with your
        application. Develop your application in the OpenEngSB environment and scripts to embed your application into
        the OpenEngSB are provided. In addition easy blending allows to adapt the OpenEngSB visually to your needs and
        cooperate design.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Simple Plug-Ins and Extensions</title>
        <para>The OpenEngSB provides the infrastructure for a rich Plug-In and extension system. Using maven archetypes
        Plug-Ins can be created, uploaded and provided to all other OpenEngSB installations or applications using the OpenEngSB.
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
