<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="contributor.transformations" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

    <title>Transformations</title>

    <para>
        The OpenEngSB project is able to do transformations between models for you. To accomplish this, you have
        to define the transformations. This can be done either through java objects (TransformationDescription)
        which is passed to the <link linkend="contributor.ekb.transformer">Transformation Engine</link> or by
        writing xml files which describe the transformation.        
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <para>
            As soon as there are more than one component which want to communicate with each other, the need for
            transformations between the model formats of both components is there. Through the definitions of
            transformations, the Transformation Engine is able to do such transformations for the user. The user
            only have to define the transformations and put the file into the config folder of the OpenEngSB project.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>File format</title>
        <para>
            Each transformation description file need to have the file ending ".transformation". 
            The root element of each of this files is:
            <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<transformations>
  // put your transformations here
</transformations>
]]>
          </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The root element of each transformation descriptions is:
            <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<transformation source="org.openengsb.presentation.ModelA;1.0.0" 
     target="org.openengsb.presentation.ModelB;1.0.0" 
     id="transformModelAToModelB_1">
  // put your transformation steps here
</transformation>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The attributes define the meta data about this transformation description. The source defines
            the source model from where this transformation would start. The number behind the model classname
            is the version of the model. The target attribute define the target model in which the transformation
            ends. 
        </para>
        <para>
            The id is an optional value which you can set. Since there can be unlimited many transformations
            between two models, you can add transformations for special cases. If you call the transformation engine
            you can pass a list of ids, where each of this ids must be in the transformation path so that there is a
            valid transformation.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The transformation steps</title>
        <para>
            There are a list of transformation steps (or transformation operations) you can use for your transformation
            definition which are delivered with the OpenEngSB. This operations are introduced in the following paragraphs.
            However, there is also the possibility of defining and adding of own transformation operations. More details
            about that can be read in the <link linkend="howto.addTransformationOperation"> How to add a transformation operation</link>
            section.
        </para>
        <para>
            The forward operation is the simplest operation. It just forwards a field value from a source field to a 
            target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<forward>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
</forward>
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The substring operation is a string operation. It only takes a part of the string from the source field and
            set it into the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<substring>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
     <param key="from" value="0" />
     <param key="to" value="4" />     
  </params> 
</substring>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameters define the exact values from which index to which index the string should be cut. Both options
            are optional. The from parameter has a standard value 0 and the to parameter has as standard value the length
            of the string in the source field.
        </para>
        <para>
            The concat operation is a string operation. It combines the values of the source fields and writes a string
            containing all source field strings in the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<concat>
  <source-fields>
    <source-field>field1A</source-field>
    <source-field>field2A</source-field>   
  </source-fields>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="concatString" value="#" />
  </params>
</concat>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameter concatString is optional. If set, this string is set between each source field. The standard 
            value is the empty string.
        </para>
        <para>
            The map operation maps based on the source field into another value for the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<map>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
   	<param key="dog" value="cat" />
   	<param key="hello" value="world" />
  </params> 
</map>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameters define the mapping. The example mapping means: if there stands 'dog' in the fieldA, write
            'cat' into fieldB. If no map matches, the value of fieldA will be written into fieldB.
        </para>
        <para>
            The split operation is a string operation, which splits a string based on a parameter into parts.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<split>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="splitString" value="#" />
    <param key="resultIndex" value="0" />
  </params>
</split>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            This operation splits fieldA based on the split string parameter and write the 0th result into fieldB. Example:
            fieldA='test1#test2#test3' as input would write 'test1' into fieldB.
        </para>
        <para>
            The trim operation is a string operation. It removes the blanks at the beginning and the end of the source field
            string and write the result into the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<trim>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
</trim>
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The length operation can calculate the length of an element in the source field and write the result as string
            into the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<length>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <!-- With the parameter function it is possible to define the function which calculates the length of the source field.
       It must be a function the object of the source field is supporting.
  <params>
    <param key="function" value="customLength" />
  </params>
  -->   
</length>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            With the optional parameter function you can define which function should be used to calculate the length.
            E.g. If in fieldA there is a list, you would write the value "size" into the function parameter.
        </para>
        <para>
            The replace operation is a string operation. It can be used to replace a certain part of the string in the
            source field with another string.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<replace>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="oldString" value="old" />
    <param key="newString" value="new" />
  </params>
</replace>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameters define which string should be replaced with which string. E.g. with the above definition:
            fieldA='this is old' would be changed to fieldB='this is new'.
        </para>
        <para>
            The to lower operation is a string operation which convert a string from the source field into its lower case
            equivalent and writes it to the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<toLower>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
</toLower>
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The to upper operation is a string operation which convert a string from the source field into its upper case
            equivalent and writes it to the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<toUpper>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
</toUpper>
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The value operation is used to set a constant value into a target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<value> 
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="value" value="Hello World" />     
  </params>   
</value>
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The pad operation is a string operation which takes the string of the source field and pad it
            based on the parameters and write result into the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<pad>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="length" value="4" />
    <param key="char" value="0" />
    <param key="direction" value="Start" />   
  </params>
</pad>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The length parameter defines how long the padding is done. The char parameter defines which character
            is used for the padding. The direction defines from where the padding is started. This is an optional
            parameter and its default value is Start. The other one is End.
            Example: fieldA='1' would set into fieldB='0001'
        </para>
        <para>
            The instantiate operation is used to support other field types than only strings.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<instantiate>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="targetType" value="java.lang.Integer" />
    <param key="targetTypeInit" value="parseInt" />
        <!-- optional value. If this parameter isn't set, the constructor of the target type with the object
         class of the source field as parameter will be used. Also this paramater can be a static method or 
         a instance method -->     
  </params>
</instantiate>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameter targetType defines the class which shall be used for the instantiation. The targetTypeInit
            parameter is used to define which function of the targetType is used for initiating. Here the value of
            the source field is taken as parameter. If this parameter isn't set, the constructor of the targetType
            with the source field as parameter will be used.
        </para>
        <para>
            The remove leading operation is a string operation. It takes the string from the source field and removes
            all elements at the start which match a regular expression.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<removeleading>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="regexString" value="[?#]+" />
    <param key="length" value="0" />
  </params>
</removeleading>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameter regexString defines the regular expression. The length parameter defines how long the removing
            is done at maximum. This is an optional parameter. Its default value is 0. 0 means that the whole string will
            be taken for the remove operation. Example: fieldA='??##??id' would set fieldB='id' with the parameters shown above.
        </para>
        <para>
            The reverse operation is a string operation. It takes the string from the source field, reverses it and writes
            the result into the target field.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<reverse>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>   
</value>
]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            The split regex operation is a string parameter. It works exactly like the split operation, but takes a
            regular expression as base for the splitting and not a single character.
            <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<splitRegex>
  <source-field>fieldA</source-field>
  <target-field>fieldB</target-field>
  <params>
    <param key="regexString" value="[^#]+" />
    <param key="resultIndex" value="0" />
  </params>
</splitRegex>
]]>
            </programlisting>
            The parameter regexString defines the regular expression. The parameter resultIndex defines like in
            split which result will be written into the target field. Example fieldA='value1#value2#value3' would
            result in fieldB='value1' with the above parameters.
        </para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>

