<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="how.to.read" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>How to read the Manual</title>

  <para>Like any open source project we have the problem that writing documentation is a pain and
  nobody is paid for doing it. In combination with the rapidly changing OpenEngSB
  source base this will lead to a huge mess within shortest time. To avoid this problem we've
  introduced regular documentation reviews and, more importantly, the following rules which apply
  both for writing the document and for reading it.
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>The manual is written as short and precise as possible (less text means lesser to read and even lesser to review)</listitem>
    <listitem>The manual does not describe how to use an interface but only coarse grained concepts in the OpenEngSB. Since the OpenEngSB is not an end user application, but rather a framework for developers we expect that Javadoc is no problem for them. Writing Javadoc and keep it up to date is still hard for developers, but much easier than maintaining an external document. Therefore, all concepts are explained and linked directly to the very well documented interfaces in the OpenEngSB on Github. To fully understand and use them you'll have to read this manual parallel to the interface documentation in the source code.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>

</chapter>

