<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!--

   Copyright 2010 OpenEngSB Division, Vienna University of Technology

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.

-->
<chapter id="testclient" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>How to use the OpenEngSB Testclient</title>

  <section>
    <title>Starting the Testclient</title>
    <para>
      To start the testclient run the shell script run-testclient.sh in the scripts folder. 
      This will deploy the test-jms service unit, which is used by the swing client to send messages into the OpenEngSB.
      Futher more the test client will be started by this script.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Message-Sending Tab</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata id="new" fileref="graphics/testclient_message.png"
            format="png" />
        </imageobject>
		<caption>Messaging</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>
      There are five parameters of a message that can be set using the testclient.
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>Context - the context id, which is used to distinguish between different project contexts</listitem>
        <listitem>Endpoint - The target endpoint of the message.</listitem>     
        <listitem>Operation - The operation field of the JBI message, which has to be set to "event" for event messages and to "methodcall" for service-calls</listitem>     
        <listitem>MEP - The message exchange pattern, that shall be used. Service-calls have to use in-out, whereas event messages have to use in-only or robust-in-only</listitem>     
        <listitem>Payload - The textarea can be used to define the content of the message</listitem>     
      </orderedlist>
      Note: The load button can be used to load text from a file into the content textarea.
      The list of available endpoints is built from the list of consumers specified in the xbean.xml of the openengsb-test-jms-su, which can be found
      in the directory test/jms/service-unit/src/main/resources.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    To add additional endpoints add jms:consumer elements to the xbean.xml in src/main/resources in the openengsb-test-jms-su.
    </para> 
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The Context Tab</title>
    <para>
      The context tab will only work if the context service-unit is deployed. 
      This is currently not the case if only the essential parts of the OpenEngSB are deployed.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata id="new" fileref="graphics/testclient_context.png"
            format="png" />
        </imageobject>
		<caption>Context information</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      On the left the tree structure of the context is shown. Clicking one of the nodes displays its key-value pairs in the table
      on the right side of the window. Changes can be made using the context menu, or the buttons. If the value of an entry shall be
      changed just edit it directly in the table - it will be saved when the cell loses focus after editing.
      The "Refresh" button can be used to load changes that have been made concurrently by someone else.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

