<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2010 OpenEngSB Division, Vienna University of Technology

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="developer.howto.internal.domain" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>How To Create an Internal Domain</title>

  <para>This chapter describes how to implement a domain for the OpenEngSB environment. A domain provides a common
    interface and common events on how to interact with connectors for this domain. For a better description of what a
    domain exactly consists of, take a look at the architecture guide <xref linkend="developer.chapter" />.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>In case it isn't known what a domain is and how it defines the interface and events for connectors, then (TODO
      link to architecture) is a good starting point.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating a new domain project</title>

    <para>To get developers started creating a new domain a Maven archetype is provided for creating the initial project
      structure. Furthermore, if the new domain is developed in the OpenEngSB repository, a shell script can be found at
        <literal>etc/scripts/gen-domain.sh</literal> as further convenience.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Using the Maven Archetype</title>

      <para>TBW - explain all variables</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using the <literal>gen-domain.sh</literal> shell script</title>

      <para>The script should be executed from the domains directory in your OpenEngSB repository.</para>

      <literallayout><command>domains $</command> ../etc/scripts/gen-domain.sh</literallayout>

      <para>You'll be asked to fill i a few variables the script needs to create the initial project structure. Based on
        your input, the script tries to gues further values. Guessed values are displayed in brackets. If the guess is
        correct, simply acknowledge with <literal>Return</literal>. As example, the following output has been recorded
        while creating the Test domain:</para>

      <literallayout><command>Domain Name (is mydomain):</command> test &lt;Enter>
<command>Version (is 1.0.0-SNAPSHOT):</command> &lt;Enter>
<command>Prefix for project names (is OpenEngSB :: Domains :: Test):</command> &lt;Enter></literallayout>

      <para>Only the domain name has been filled in, while the rest has been correctly guessed by the script. After
        giving the inputs, the Maven archetype gets executed and may ask for further inputs. You can simply hit
          <literal>Return</literal>, as the values have been already correctly set by the script. If the script finishes
        successfully two new Maven projects, the domain parent and domain implementation project, have been created and
        setup with a sample implementation for a domain.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Project structure</title>

      <para>The newly created domain should have the exact same structure as the following listing:</para>

      <programlisting>-- implementation
|  -- pom.xml
|  -- src
|     -- main
|     |  -- java
|     |  -- org
|     |     -- openengsb
|     |        -- domains
|     |           -- test
|     |              -- MyDomain.java
|     |              -- MyDomainEvents.java
|     |              -- MyDomainProvider.java
|     -- resources
|        -- META-INF
|        |   -- spring
|        |      -- notification-context.xml
|        -- OSGI-INF
|           -- l10n
|              -- bundle_de.properties
|              -- bundle.properties
-- pom.xml</programlisting>

      <para>TBW - explain structure</para>

      <para>Although the generated domain does in effect nothing, you can already start the OpenEngSB for testing with
          <literal>mvn clean install pax:provision</literal> and the domain will be automatically be picked up and started.</para>

      <para>TBW - Spring DM</para>

      <para>Each OpenEngSB bundle (core, domain, connector) has been designed with localization in mind. E.g. the Maven
        Archetype already creates to <literal>bundle*.properties</literal> files, one for English (bundle.properties)
        and one for the German (bundle_de.properties) language. Each connector has to provide localization through the
        properties files. For domains, this only means localization for a name and description of the domain
        itself.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Customizing</title>

      <para>TBW</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Integrating the Domain into the OpenEngSB environment</title>

    <para>TBW</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Components</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Domain interface - This is the interface that connectors of that domain must implement. Operations that
          connectors should provide, are specified here. Events that are raised by this Domain in unexpected fashion 
          (e.g new commit in scm system) are specified on the Interface. The Raise Annotation and the array of Event 
          classes it takes as an argument are used. If the Raise annotation is put on a method the events that 
          are specified through the annotation are raised in sequence upon a call.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Domain event interface - This is the interface that the domain provides for its connectors to send events
        into the OpenEngSB. The event interface contains a <literal>raiseEvent(SomeEvent event)</literal> method for each 
        supported event type.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Domain Provider - The domain provider is a service that provides information about the domain itself. It
          is used to determine which domains are currently registered in the environment. There is an abstract class,
          that takes over most of the setup.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Spring context - There are three services, that must be registered with the OSGi service-environment. First
          there is the domainprovider of course. Moreover the domain must provide a kind of connector itself, since it
          must be able to handle service calls and redirect it to the default-connector specified in the current
          context. And finally the domain provides an event interface for its connectors, which can be used by them to send
          events into the OpenEngSB. The default implementation of this event interface simply forwards all events sent through
          the domain to the workflow service. But domains can also provide their own implementation of their event interface and
          add data to events or perform other tasks. There is a beanfactory that creates a Java-Proxy that can be used as 
          ForwardService both for the forwarding of service calls from domain to connector and for the forwarding of events to
          the workflow service. The service call ForwardService looks up the default-connector for the specified domain in the
          current context and forwards the method-call right to it. The event forward service simply forwards all events to 
          the workflow service of the OpenEngSB.</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<osgi:service>
  <osgi:interfaces>
    <!-- Every Connector must be registered with the Domain-interface -->
    <value>org.openengsb.core.common.Domain</value>
    <!-- The domain-interface goes here-->
    <value>org.openengsb.domains.notification.NotificationDomain</value>
  </osgi:interfaces>
  <osgi:service-properties>
    <!-- The convention for the service-id is "domains.<domain-name>" -->
    <entry key="id" value="domains.notification" />
    <!-- To allow other services (e.g. workflow) to distinguish the forward-service 
      from other connector-instances, this attribute must be set to "domain" -->
    <entry key="openengsb.service.type" value="domain" />
  </osgi:service-properties>
  <!-- use the bean-factory to generate the forward-service -->
  <bean class="org.openengsb.core.common.DefaultDomainProxyFactoryBean">
    <!-- Need to specify the domain-interface again -->
    <property name="domainInterface">
      <value>org.openengsb.domains.notification.NotificationDomain</value>
    </property>
    <!-- this is used as a lookup-key in the context -->
    <property name="domainName" value="NotificationDomain" />
    <!-- reference to the context-service (obtained below) -->
    <property name="context" ref="contextService" />
  </bean>
</osgi:service>

<osgi:service>
  <osgi:interfaces>
    <!-- The common domain event marker interface, each domain events interface has to 
      extend -->
    <value>org.openengsb.core.common.DomainEvents</value>
    <!-- The specific event interface containing the raiseEvent methods -->
    <value>org.openengsb.domains.notification.NotificationDomainEvents</value>
  </osgi:interfaces>
  <osgi:service-properties>
  <!-- The convention for the service-id is "domains.<domain-name>.events" -->
    <entry key="id" value="domains.notification.events" />
    <entry key="openengsb.service.type" value="domain-events" />
  </osgi:service-properties>
  <!-- the default implementation of the event interface is provided by this class, 
    which generates a proxy that forwards all events to the workflow service, 
    obtained below -->
  <bean class="org.openengsb.core.events.DomainEventsProxyFactoryBean">
    <property name="domainEventInterface">
      <!-- the domain event interface (same as above in the osgi:interfaces section -->
      <value>org.openengsb.domains.notification.NotificationDomainEvents</value>
    </property>
    <property name="workflowService" ref="workflowService" />
  </bean>
</osgi:service>

<osgi:reference id="workflowService" 
  interface="org.openengsb.core.workflow.WorkflowService" />
<osgi:reference id="contextService" 
  interface="org.openengsb.core.common.context.ContextService" />]]>
        </programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

</chapter>
