<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    
    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
    
-->

<chapter xml:id="howto.edbbackend" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">
    
    <title>HowTo - Change EDB database backend</title>
    
    <section>
        <title>Goal</title>
        <para>This tutorial describes how to change the database which is used by the EDB to persist OpenEngSBModels.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Time to Complete</title>
        <para>The time needed to perform this task depends heavily on which database you want to use instead of the standard H2 
            database and on your experience with the OpenEngSB. This capter will list the different possibilities from the shortest
            time period needed to the most complex one. If you are not familiar with the OpenEngSB please read this manual from 
            the start or check the <link xlink:href="http://www.openengsb.org">homepage</link> for further information.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Use openJPA compatible database</title>
        <para> If you want to replace the standard database with another openjpa supported database
            (supported databases listet <link
                xlink:href="http://openjpa.apache.org/builds/1.0.2/apache-openjpa-1.0.2/docs/manual/supported_databases.html"
                >here</link>), the procedure of changing is rather simple. You have to change the
            properties for the database connection of the "infrastructure/jpa" bundle. This is done by
            changing the config file "org.openengsb.infrastructure.jpa.cfg". This file is in the
            "assembly/src/main/filtered-resources/etc" folder. This file has following entries:
            <programlisting>
                  driverClassName=[here shall be the name of your driver class name, 
                     example: org.h2.jdbcx.JdbcDataSource]
                  url=[here shall be the url to the used database file, example: jdbc:h2:openengsb]
                  username=[here shall be the username for authentication at the database]
                  password=[here shall be the password for authentication at the database]
            </programlisting>
            After changing of this file, you have to assure that the driver which shall be used by
            the datasource is loaded at runtime. For that you have to load the database driver
            before the connection to the database is established. Your database bundle dependency
            should be added to the "parents/shared/pom.xml" file. A dependency entry for the h2
            database looks like this (the h2.version is defined as property in the same
            file:
            <programlisting>
              &lt;dependency>
                 &lt;groupId>com.h2database&lt;/groupId>
                 &lt;artifactId>h2&lt;/artifactId>
                 &lt;version>${h2.version}&lt;/version>
              &lt;/dependency>
            </programlisting>
            After you added the dependency, you have to make sure the database is loaded before the
            database connection is established. For that just replace following code line in the
            file "assembly/src/main/filtered-resources/features.xml" with the new database driver
            bundle (as you can see you only have to copy and paste the values of the dependency):
            <programlisting>
               &lt;bundle>mvn:com.h2database/h2/${h2.version}&lt;/bundle>
            </programlisting>
            After this steps, you are done and the EDB uses now the new database as persistence
            backend. 
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Use not openJPA compatible database</title>
        <para>
            If you want to replace the standard database with another non openjpa supported database you will have
            to change first the datasource like described in the previous section. After that you have to write your own
            bundle that provides the EngineeringDatabaseService. In this case you also have to reproduce all SQL
            commands and port it for the new database and replace the standard EngineeringDatabaseService.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Appendix: Use no OSGI compatible database</title>
        <para>
            In this case you have to wrap the driver for the database. How to do that can be read in the developer
            manual where the wrapping is explained.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
