<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    
    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
    
-->

<chapter xml:id="howto.definemodel" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
    http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

    <title>How to define a domain model</title>
    
    <section>
        <title>Goal</title>
        <para>
            This tutorial explains how to define a domain model for a specific domain. What a domain model is, can be
            read in the user manual in the semantics section(<xref linkend="user.semantics" />). The structure of a
            domain model is an interface which extends the OpenEngSBModel.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Time to complete</title>
        <para>
            If you are already familiar with the OpenEngSB about 10 minutes. If you are not familiar with the OpenEngSB 
            please read this manual from the start or check the <link xlink:href="http://www.openengsb.org">homepage</link> 
            for further information.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Prerequisites</title>
        <para>
            For information about how to get started as contributor to the OpenEngSB project and how to
            get the current OpenEngSB source please read the contributor section of the manual: 
            <xref linkend="developer.manual" />.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Step 1 - Plan the structure of the model</title>
        <para>
            The first thing to do is to think about the structure of the model you need. Think about which informations
            are needed and should be included. (e.g. if you want to create a domain model for an appointment domain, the
            domain model will contain informations like start time, end time, title, ...).
        </para>
        <para>
            Also give a think about if there exists a field which has the potential to be the id of a model. Such a field
            has to be unique for a specific domain and connector combination. Such an id can be defined through an annotation
            with the name OpenEngSBModel.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Step 2 - Write the model</title>
        <para>
            Writing a model is quite simple. A domain model is an interface, which contains only pairs of getter and
            setter methods. The method names define the internal names of the fields of the model. Example model:
        </para>
        <programlisting>
            interface Appointment extends OpenEngSBModel {
                 @OpenEngSBModel
                 void setId(Integer id);
                 Integer getId();
                 
                 void setStartTime(Date startTime);
                 Date getStartTime();
                 
                 void setEndTime(Date endTime);
                 Date getEndTime();
                 
                 ...
            }
        </programlisting>
        <para>
            This model defines a part of a domain model for an appointment domain. In this model we also have defined
            the id of the model, with the name id. You can see that through the set annotation.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Step 3 - Add the model to a domain</title>
        <para>
            The last step is to add the model to the specific domain. For that you simply have to add the model
            to the model package in the specific domain. Now the model is ready to use in the connectors for the
            specific domain.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Step 4 - Use the model</title>
        <para>
            The last step is to use the model. For that you have to use a util class which is placed in the core/common
            bundle called ModelUtils. An instantiation of a model looks like this:
        </para>
        <programlisting>
            Appointment appointment = ModelUtils.createEmptyModelObject(Appointment.class);
        </programlisting>
        <para>
            After that you can use the appointment object like a normal instantiated object.
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>