<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Licensed to the Austrian Association for Software Tool Integration (AASTI)
    under one or more contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file
    distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright
    ownership. The AASTI licenses this file to you under the Apache License,
    Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
    with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter xml:id="howto.workflow-editor" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd
  http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance.xsd">

  <title>HowTo - Use the workflow Editor</title>
  <para>This HowTo will show the basics of creating and editing a Workflow in the Editor.
    As the Editor is still very much under development this is a current preview version.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Elements of the Workflow</title>
    <para>The Workflow Editor currently uses Actions and Events to describe Workflows. </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Action</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An Action calls a specific method on a connector instance. Every Action can have 
            follow up Actions that will be called after the connector method was executed. You can
            also add Events to an Action. If the method you call on an Action has @Raises Annotations
            and thus raises Events you can add Handlers for that Event.</para>
          <para>You can edit the code that is executed in the Action. When setting the Domain, Method
            and Location the Action should execute you can create a template Method call.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Event</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When a connector method raises an Event you can add a Handler for that. An Event
            gets an associated Action that should be executed whenever the Event is raised.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>When starting the WorkflowEditor you have to create a Workflow if none already exists. When
      creating a Workflow you have to set a root Action which gets executed as the first step of
      the workflow.</para>
    <para>After creating the workflow you can either add Actions or Events to your current workflow, create
      another workflow or, if you already created various workflows, choose which one you want to edit.</para>
    <para>The workflows are currently only held in memory in a service that will support storage and retrieval
      upon restart at a later stage.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Exporting a Workflow</title>
    <para>You can export the currently selected Workflow at any time, by pressing the Export button in the
      WorkflowEditor. The Workflow will be exported to the RuleManager and should then be visible and
      executable on the SendEvent Page.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>

