<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2010 OpenEngSB Division, Vienna University of Technology

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<chapter id="pimDomain" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title id="pimDomain.title">PIM Domain</title>
  
  <warning>
    <para>
      This page is only a proposal! This means that everyone is allowed to edit this page and it is 
      marked for change. This proposal could be seen as design idea and should be discussed in public
      and visible for everyone before implemented at all.
    </para>
  </warning>
  
  <para>
   This proposal is about an additional domain at the engineering service bus. The domain is responsible for connecting
   a range of <emphasis>p</emphasis>ersonal <emphasis>i</emphasis>nformation <emphasis>m</emphasis>anagement systems (PIM). Generally there could be thought about tasks,
   persons, calendars, time-tracking and so on. Mostly I think in the direction of the KDE Akonadi project, but not
   as a local common datastore, more as a global sync server. This means we have to implement a wide range of different
   protocols and connectors. Very interesting connectors could be gcal (calendar), gmail (contacts), rtm (tasks),
   direct mailer integration, which means global icals file (mail), "pseudo" ldap server (contacts), and maybe some
   additional protocols. This would allow developers to have access to all his tasks, mettings, persons of the project
   and so on in his own environment. He could use google, rtm, outlook, kontact, evolution, 
   imacthingihavenoideaandiamnotinterestedinhowthisthingisnamed and so on. He could close tasks, add comments to tasks
   which will be attached to issue tracker issues, he'll automatically see if a project manager changes a milestone,
   and many many other advantages.
  </para>
</chapter>